the mental side of trading can be brutal
it can take you on some of the highest
highs imaginable or drag you down to
some of the deepest lows that you'll
ever experience it reveals and exposes
things about yourself that you didn't
even know were there and challenges you
in so many different ways it's like a
roller coaster ride now on YouTube I've
seen popping up lots of these videos
that say something like how I beat the
mental game of trading after 4 years of
failing or 5 years of failing let's be
honest most of those people probably
have never actually been eaten the
mental game of trading but even if they
have those amounts of time might sound
significant but they're really not in
the grand scheme of things so I first
started learning about the markets back
in 2002 that's over 20 years ago and in
2012 I gave up my career in banking to
become a full-time Trader and start
trading for a living so that's coming up
to 13 years ago and I can tell you after
all of this time four to 5 years is
barely scratching the surface there are
so many things that you will experience
that will be revealed to you exposed and
that you'll go through that will show
you that you knew very little at that
point different Market Cycles uh when
you have more capital and you're making
bigger profits bigger losses maybe
managing money on behalf of other people
different phases of Life different
things that will impact your trading
from the outside there are so many
lessons to be learned in fact I've even
spoken about it in a video on this
channel that one of my worst moments
psychologically from Trading was when
I'd already been trading for a decade
I'd made hundreds of thousands of pounds
in profits I was trading full-time I'd
managed capital on behalf of other
people and that's when it hit me the
absolute hardest and I had a a meltdown
I got really ill from it and at that
time I thought I knew everything there
was to know about the mental side of
trading and in hindsight and that was
probably about 10 years or so ago now I
realized I didn't know as much as I
thought so because I think those videos
most likely don't cover the right things
or they're not actually talking from
experience they're just wanting to put
together a video because they've seen
that that Topic's doing well I thought
that I would put together a video going
through 15 principles or actions that I
know for a fact will actually improve
your trading psychology now I know
everyone's different everyone's mindset
is different everything that people have
been through is going to be different
different experiences different view on
the world different obstacles and
problems and so on and so on so it's not
like trading psychology can be a one-
siiz fits-all approach but I guarantee
to you if you follow these 15 principles
or actions you'll be 90% of the way
there this will sort out most trading
psychology problems you could go through
through most people if you follow this
you won't have any problems anymore this
is based on my experience as I said I've
been trading for over 20 years now it's
based on helping hundreds maybe even
thousands depending on how you classify
it Traders around the world to come like
to overcome these problems and to
improve their trading and it's based on
extensive research I use evidence-based
information we actually dig into the
studies and find out what works from
neuroscience and psychology not just
this received wisdom unfounded opinions
that you see everywhere else this
wishy-washy pseudo science this stuff is
evidence-based however and I'm going to
share my screen now when we go through
these points you're going to see that
this isn't scripted so I can't cite the
research for you because I don't
remember all of it off the top of my
head I remember the essence of it but
not exactly who it was by or the year it
was published so what I'll do is in the
description box you'll find links to
different videos that we've done
covering these specific topics or I'll
mention that there's a video coming up
soon and of course if it's not scripted
those of you that have watched our
videos before will know that it's likely
to be quite a long video I'm going to be
sometimes going on tangents and telling
stories or rambling and some people love
that approach cuz they like the Nuance
the discussion and some people hate it
so with that in mind if you're the type
of Karen who rushes down to the comments
section to write things like you're
taking too long to get to the point
you're talking a lot but not saying
enough then stop being so entitled this
is a free video it's free information
you're not being forced to watch it you
can just save your time and effort and
go somewhere else you're not going to be
able to speak to my manager the buck
stops with me and I don't care so hit
the dislike button and just [__] off no
one needs to see the comment but anyway
with that out of the way let's get to
the first point which is to ground
yourself with realistic expectations I'm
going to apologize straight away my
handwriting is terrible but I want to
draw all over this as we go along so
there are two things that are the
absolute worst for people that are
learning to trade it's two things we've
got urgency and scarce it and these are
going to come up a lot now there's
another thing which is down here and
we'll say it's
patience now everyone talks about with
patience it's about waiting for the
right entry being patient enough not to
force things and to overtrade and that
kind of thing I would call that micro
patience we'll talk about this as we go
along as with these other two points as
well but there's also macro patients
which is all about your development and
it all relates to to this feeling of
urgency now social media has made it
really difficult for people to have
realistic expectations because there are
two things that you see on social media
it's huge returns I'm going do huge
percentage here and short timelines so
what happens I've seen this one in our
community loads you get people who are
sensible people who understand that
trading is not about making hundreds of%
returns every month but still have dist
orted views on what realistic returns
are even if they think they're being
realistic they still have distorted
views on it because social media has
distorted everyone's opinion on trading
so much you see when I first started
learning about trading I was reading
books yeah I'm kind of ancient like you
were couldn't go online and watch a
YouTube video back then it was like
there were bulletin boards that were
really [__] and they were for like small
cap equities most of the time but
instead it was books and people didn't
really talk about insane returns it was
more about the process and so I
developed curiosity for the markets
which then developed into a passion for
the markets and I'm going to put that
over here and we're going to also refer
to this so
curiosity which then develops into
passion but these days someone can
progress of their trading develop the
skill and be amazing with their trading
I've see it all the time with our
members and then be making like 1% to 5%
a month because here's the thing we've
talked about this in the video before
let's say that this is your trading and
this line here is break even and all the
time that you're learning you're kind of
losing down here it's not like when you
become consistently profitable that you
jump from here to like 100% return up
here that it comes up here oh I'm
consistently profitable now so I'm now
making like mega bucks no it's like this
there's Break Even you're learning
losing losing you start losing a bit
less you stay around break even for a
while and you start like drifting a
little bit higher and a little bit
higher you hit plateaus and on you might
be at like 1% of 1% return per month on
average for a very long time and guess
what that's amazing because that's
better than 95% of the market you know
these stats where it's like 95% of
Traders lose and maybe it's 90% in some
case or 80% whatever stat you want to
believe in I like to think it's
95% that doesn't say 95% of Traders are
sorry 5% of Traders are making profit
that's saying 95% are losing which means
that from the remaining 5% is also
counting people who are not losing and
not making a profit I.E balances at the
Brokers that have not been touched when
people deposit money and don't trade it
when people have traded it but have no
Edge and haven't been losing and end up
at break even so actually the percentage
of traders who are profiting will be
even less so if you're making an average
of 1% per month Bravo you're doing a
[__] good job then because most
people are not doing that but what
happens when people start making these
returns because they've got unrealistic
expectations they think well it's not
20% a month I'm not really good at
trading because I'm only making that but
hold on a second what other industry
could you be in the top less than 5%
like let's say top 3% top 4% if you want
to be generous being in that top amount
and still think that you're a bad Trader
it's cuz social media has disrupted
everyone's view of what it actually
means to trade what is realistic what's
achievable what's sustainable that's the
important word here sustainable and so
social media is full of idiots that have
just ruined this [__] industry and
made it embarrassing to tell people
you're a Trader that's something that we
could discuss another time you know what
I sound really bitter and it's cuz I am
bitter I've decided this year I'm so
sick of this industry and what it's
become I'm just going to say it how it
is from now on I don't really care about
coming across is like I'm going to be
nice nice about everything I'll just say
it how it is this industry is assess
pool these days and most of the people
on YouTube are just don't know what
they're talking about and all they're
doing is leading people to a path of
actually failing because even if they
don't think they are even if they're
teaching things that they think is
useful information when they start
putting amounts of money in their
YouTube titles and stuff like that and
quoting these ridiculous returns in
their videos because they think it's
going to get more clicks and Views they
don't realize that they are embedding in
people's minds a certain belief about
what trading is that's going to lead
them astray or make them feel
perpetually disappointed with what
they're doing and end up giving up and
feel frustrated they don't realize that
that's what they're doing and what's it
in Aid of just for them to get some
clicks and to get people buying their
rubbish training no thank you anyway I
told you this video is going to go on
and I've just already gone on a big
tangent so that's the first problem the
next problem is the short timelines you
see when people say that they've gone
from selling fast foods not that you
have a fast food salesman but serving
fast food and 2 years later driving a
Lambo then that's going to make you
think that you need to progress in two
years which is not going to give you the
macro patience it's going to give you
urgency which means that rather than
thinking about I'm going to progress and
do things in the right way you're going
to realize 6 months down the line 12
months down the line [__] if I want to
be in a Lambo two like two years down
the line I haven't progressed enough so
then you start pushing things too
quickly moving on to Trading in the live
markets with real money tooo soon not
really caring about developing the skill
just caring about how quickly can I get
to trading and making money so you need
to ground yourself with realistic
expectations what you need to realize
and we'll discuss this as well is that
trading is well being a Trader is a
profession and trading is a complex
skill it's a multifaceted skill with
lots of smaller skills that come
together to to be trading and it takes
time to learn that and it's not
something that you're going just learn
overnight or go for two years like think
about it in two years you'd have to have
learned the skill and made enough money
to have achieved the lambo either
they're not following their risk
parameters that they're teaching to
everyone and if that if they're not
following that then you know are you
going to trust in someone teaching you
that can't even follow the things
they're teaching you or they're lying or
they have those of capital to start with
I'd say it's most likely that they're
lying and then the final thing I almost
forgot I said I'd come back to it is
that the best way to avid void rushing
to this end destination of making lots
of money from Trading and to actually go
through the process the right way and
develop the skill the right way is to be
actually curious about what you're
learning to be interested in the markets
to be interested in different aspects of
trading and to sort of dive into that
Curiosity and eventually it will develop
into a passion that's what happened for
me like I didn't start trading because I
thought I'd make money from it CU I
didn't really know about trading I just
knew that the markets were fascinating
it seemed bigger than I was which is
true
and it just seemed like this huge thing
that I can just research and understand
and I wanted to learn everything I could
about it and it developed into a passion
where over 20 years later I'm still
studying so many aspects of trading I'm
digging into research about Psychology
and Neuroscience just to understand more
about how it affects our trading and I
can put together videos like this
because of it I'm researching the way
the markets work like the underlying
mechanisms and stuff so I can understand
why prices are moving the way they are
developing theories understanding other
people's theories and so on and so on
spending my life basically talking about
trading as well I know some people think
that we make loads of money from selling
our program but the fact is we publish
our financial figures on the website on
D initiative.com and you can see that
the amount we make in Revenue doesn't
even cover our costs I'm not making any
money from this I'm actually spending
money every month to keep the company
alive that's another thing for another
time but anyway let's move on to the
second Point uh but sorry just to to
reiterate there like by developing a
passion it means less likely to rush
ahead because you're enjoying the
learning process it's not just about the
making money you're intrinsically
motivated not just extrinsically
motivated which is the better way to
succeed so I told you it's going to be a
long video grab your coffee I know I
don't support the Patriots I just like
the size of the mug I mean the mug could
say like go meth and I'd still drink
from it unless it says go Spurs you know
we all have our limits there's no way
I'm drinking out of that so the second
point is related to the first in the way
it's word but actually it's a very
different point and it's to set the
right expectations for others or don't
tell them now there are a few ways that
this is going to impact you the first
thing is pressure in fact it's all
pressure but what a lot of people do is
they get excited about trading and they
want to tell people around them friends
family uh partner kids who knows and
when they tell them about it they're not
explaining to them the realistic stuff
like we very rarely do when we're
excited about something we tell people
the good side so in other words when
we're telling people about trading when
we're getting excited about learning it
and we want them to back us on that
Journey we're selling them the dream so
what happens is they haven't got the
view of the downside of it all because
they don't maybe know about trading in
the way that you do and all they think
is like okay so you're going to learn
this for a while and then you're going
to make mega bucks and our life is going
to change and of course you want them to
believe that cuz you want them to be
excited about what you're doing as well
and so we can say that one the things
that leads to pressure is people being
sold the dream now you might have been
sold the dream as well but you need to
get to reality like we just discussed
with the first point but when others
have
been sold the dream it's going to put
pressure on you because now you
have
expectations about timelines about
amounts of money and what happens when
you don't meet those
expectations you start feeling
feeling like a failure you start feeling
like a failure related to that is also
from the last point the having
expectations for yourself one of the
most common phrases that I hear from
young men that tell me about the
negative mental problems they're going
through is this expression here I feel
like I'm
being left
behind because everyone else went in for
a corporate career and they're
progressing and getting promotions and
you started focusing on your trading and
now you feel like they're progressing to
making money more money and you're not
but because you chose to go and learn a
different profession it's going to take
time but you're going to start feeling
like a failure if this is what you start
feeling and if other people have
expectations that you're not meeting
because you didn't give them realistic
expectations you're going to feel like a
failure and what's that going to do it's
going to make it much more difficult to
focus on the process so can't focus on
the pro
process on
process and it's going to want you to
fast TR make you want to fast trck
things which is a recipe for disaster
cuz you're not going to be ready for it
you're going to feel like why do I need
to keep practicing stuff why do I need
to work and developing my system why do
I need to be back testing why can't I
just be yoloing all of my money and not
feeling like a failure anymore when am I
going to retire my parents so setting
the right expectations for others it's
important that you
manage
expectations be realistic say to them
there's the possibility I could do
really well from this there's a
possibility that I could be wasting my
time and it will never work for me and
it will be frustrating there's also a
chance that it could work for me but
it's going to be just a reasonable
reasonable amount of money and maybe I
could make more from doing something
else doing a different side Hustle but I
really am passionate about the markets
I'm interested in this it's not just
about the money so even though there are
other options that are maybe easier and
have more of a guarantee of making money
this is the one that interests me the
most you might be able to say to them
there are going to be times when it gets
tough mentally there are going to be
times where I feel like my self-esteem's
taking a knock or I'm frustrated or I'm
stressed I need you to understand that's
what I'm going to be going through so
when I'm going through those times don't
start expecting something from me or
like telling me off for it or something
like I will need support during those
times there was this amazing thing that
happened a few years
ago this woman got in touch with me and
she said that her boyfriend had been
learning to trade for a while four or
five years and he was a really smart guy
like a mathematician or an engineer or
something and she wanted me to have a
call with him he didn't know that she'd
arranged this because she was worried
about his mental health and I spoke to
the guy and they were sat there together
and it was so to me it was so lovely
that the girlfriend had thought how can
she support him best she's going to
reach out to someone who he had been
watching my videos and like trusted my
my point of view so we had this Skype
call and you know is she was supporting
him she was saying like you are the most
intelligent amazing guy and you can
achieve all these things and you're
working so hard but he couldn't accept
that uh he was not succeeding like at
the rate that he wanted to I mean it got
really emotional at one point but anyway
I won't go into like all of what was
discussed and stuff but the important
part there was because she had the right
expectations and the right understanding
of it she was able to take actions that
actually supported him and I got emails
from them afterwards that things were
much better because of that like he just
needed a bit of a pep talk from someone
who had been there and done it so
there's all of that then there's
also that
people don't approve you see the problem
is some parents want you to be a doctor
or a lawyer and if you're not going to
be a doctor or lawyer you're an
embarrassment to the family and it's
just how it is but also people have this
perception of trading because of the
[__] idiots that I spoke about
earlier who have made trading seem like
the new Herbal Life or something like
multi-level marketing I've mentioned
before on Instagram about when I went to
a wedding and I was sat next to this
girl who I'd not really spoken to before
and she said what do you do for a living
and I used to tell people different
stories and stuff but I just said I
trade for a living and she said oh is
that what those love Island type people
do on Instagram and I was like [__] my
life this is the perception people have
of trading these days so of course
people are not going to approve because
they want to protect you but what
happens is that's going to feed into
self-doubt and frustration
and feeling like a failure so if you
think that your family are not going to
approve don't tell your family don't
tell them until you're actually
succeeding like do they need to know
other things that you're doing with your
time if you're watching football or porn
or whatever else you're doing do they
need to know about that as well probably
not so you don't need to tell them if
you're spending time learning trading
either
and then just related to this is also
there are different studies about this
but the most recent and the most
convincing one is that you should not
talk about your goals should not talk
about goals now as I said
earlier I can't cite you the exact
findings of the research because I'm
doing this off the top of my head but it
essentially is that you're getting some
sort of dopamine hit from like a social
dopamine hit I'll have to Fig find the
the right terminology it was social
something but basically from talking
about it your brain is feeling like you
are getting the rewards that you should
be getting from achieving the thing you
see ultimately we're doing all of this
for uh survival having money resources
to be able to ensure our survival but
also status which is related to survival
so if we're getting status by telling
someone about what we're going to be
achieving it's kind of satisfying the
need for us so we shouldn't talk about
our goals anyway I think the only time
you should talk to your people around
you about trading while you're learning
is if you know you're going to need the
support from them and or if they're
going to be wondering what you're doing
with your time if it's necessary for
them to know if not then just don't
bother telling them I think it's just
safer that way there's too many things
that can go wrong I've heard too many
disasters from it all and the absolute
worst please never do this it's like
when someone starts learning to trade
they've started to make money for
themselves and they get excited and tell
everyone and everyone's like oh can you
do it with my money and my money and my
money and my money and then suddenly
recipe
okay so next one get your foundations in
order I know this sounds simple but
here's the thing if I said to you okay
there's this simple trick that you can
Implement right now like you see this
all over YouTube it's all the little
things where it's like trading was hard
until I figured this thing out by the
way we're going to start using these
titles cuz no one watches our videos
when we say things that are
straightforward people want this sort of
clickbait rubbish SO trading was hard
until I figured out this thing or this
simple trick will increase your
profitability by x% increase your
success rate with this one simple thing
the strategy they don't want to tell you
about blah blah blah here's the reality
if I gave you one I said it's guaranteed
to improve your performance by 10 15%
you'd take it you'd pay money for it if
it was guaranteed but getting your
foundations in order will achieve
exactly that for you and this is
something that people neglect and it's
something that I neglected I've talked
about before you'll find it linked down
below or I'll put it up on screen as
well my experiences of when I first
started making big money from Trading
hundreds of thousands of L pound and I
got so ill I had a meltdown a breakdown
and like I thought I dying like I
actually contemplated suicide at the
time cuz my my chemistry my brain must
have been so [__] and stuff at the
time um you can watch the video and
understand all of that but basically it
was lack of sleep I was trading around
the clock I thought I don't want to miss
an opportunity so don't sleep I was
sleeping like 2 3 hours a night my sleep
to this day is still ruined from what
happened back then but if you can get
your foundations in order it's going to
improve things in so many ways so first
of all it's going to improve cognitive
performance performance to do perform
like that it's going to improve
cognitive performance so you're actually
going to make decisions better you're
going to see things on the charts better
you're going to be sharper quicker
quicker reactions you're going to be so
much better learn quicker everything as
a result of
sleeping 8 hours a night 7 and a half
whatever you need exercising now there's
views on this but I would say if you can
exercise uh like just do some sort of um
not too demanding steady state cardio at
least every day meaning basically going
for a walk outside uh for like half an
hour to 40 minutes that'll be pretty
good and doing something a bit more
active like me personally I work out
every day for about 40 minutes well
that's four or five times a week and I
go for a walk do over 10,000 steps every
single day and it's the best thing for
your mental health and everything um so
I'm going to leave leave this one blank
but I'll say like at least like 45
minutes of like walking or something
like that nutrition your brain is what
you're using for your trading and your
brain is extremely metabolically
expensive there are studies done on
chess Grandmasters who burn through
thousands of calories during a
tournament and you can imagine a
decision- making you're you're doing
with your brain with your brain where
else you're going to do it uh well you
can do it with other things and it gets
you in trouble trust me um the amount of
decision and focus your spending during
a trading session you're burning through
calories so you're going to need to
replenish that so you need to have a
balanced diet we've gone through lots of
studies that are in our Trader
development program by the way in the
trader development program I think of
might have mentioned that we've got over
20 hours of trading psychology lessons
which includes every aspect of it from
ways to overcome sort of deeply embedded
issues that you might have preventing
issues all research based uh optimizing
your well-being and we look at nutrition
and what the studies show is that a
Mediterranean diet is going to be best
for cognitive function and if you want
to know when the best time to eat is
then the first thing you should do is
actually track it in your trading
journal so track when you ate how you
felt during your trading session how is
your decision- making and then you can
actually find Trends in like what works
best for you but um otherwise what the
studies show is that is more like a
pyramid if you imagine this is your
total calories for the day you want to
have more of them early so breakfast
lunch dinner uh you don't want to have
your heavy meals at the end of the day
breaks you're going to need lots of
breaks there's lots lots and lots of
studies about this but for maintaining
Focus same for nutrition and everything
like if you want to maintain Focus
you're going to need to go on brakes the
best thing you can do is to go on a
break outside nature is like a vitamin
there are so many things that about
being outside what it does to your
mental health what it does to your focus
I don't want to get into the specifics
but basically when we are focused on a
problem then we have like a narrow
attentional field of view like we're
we're narrowly focused on the problem
especially if we're stressed in Narrows
when we're out in nature we our our
attention view expands and that helps
replenish the sort of more narrow
attention view as I said I'm doing this
off the top of my head so I can't give
you the exact wording that's from the
studies but we spoke about all of this
in a video on uh selft talk negative
selft talk so it was the first video
where we explained why and how negative
selft talk happens and how it affects
your trading negatively and then the
second one was the selft talk tool kit
so we'll link those down below in the
description box but you need to get
outside and like not just take a break
where you're scrolling on your phone
that's not going to help you recover
it's actually going to make things worse
and again there's another video down
below where it talks about the right
sort of braks to have so all of them
improve cognitive performance all of
these as well are going to help reduce
or um avoid
stress particularly the one that lots of
young men don't give enough attention to
which is sleep because they think sleep
when you're dead like I did but I've
changed my tune on that uh sleep is
necessary for reducing stress likewise
if you're hungry you're going to get
more stressed exercise is going to give
you a cocktail of neurochemicals that's
going to help reduce stress make you
feel better same with getting outside
and so on and trading is stressful
learning to trade is stressful all the
pressure everything so if you want to
reduce stress get your foundations in
order the rest goes about saying uh
hydrate properly you know if you don't
drink enough water if you're slightly
dehydrated it starts to get to the
equivalent of actually having drank a
bit of alcohol like in terms of how you
function cognitively so if you want to
improve your performance get your
foundations in order it's going to avoid
a lot of the trading psychology issues I
mean think about when people get hangry
and stuff well that's obviously the the
food is affecting their brain you know
we we need homeostasis
then like all these different things are
sort of leading towards that and when we
don't have homeostasis or when things
are in disorder then it's going to have
an impact on the way we make decisions
our emotions our feelings our attitudes
our everything okay so the next point is
don't learn to trade with real money now
this is something that a lot of people
will disagree with me on because they
say that you can't learn to trade with
fake money because trading is so about
trading psychology and when there's real
money on the line then it feels more
real and your decision making changes
and blah blah blah blah blah I get it
it's important at some point to be in
your development to have real money but
only when you're ready for it you don't
do that right at the start you go
through different phases and then you
move on to having real money because
even if you are profitable in a demo
account when you start trading with real
money it can change things a lot uh
there's a video we'll have coming out of
some point of someone that felt a
difference between being profitable in
their demo account this one of our
members very profitable in their demo
account ready to go for funding went
through the funding process and it's
almost like all of the principles
they've been following everything went
out the window and they're trading a bit
like an amateur at times and we talk
about why that happens and how to avoid
it but there's an important reason so
that's the point of like why you need to
learn with real money at some point but
if you learn at the start with real
money it can cause a disaster first of
all obviously you're going to lose money
but that's not related to trading
psychology directly the thing that is
related to trading psychology is
conditioned
responses now conditioned
response is an automatic Behavior that's
triggered by a stimulus that should have
been neutral or was previously neutral
so the famous example of this is
Pavlov's dogs does that ring a bell
sorry terrible but Dad joke there um but
these are basically Auto why did I say
that on camera jeez automatic
behaviors
now again I can't give you the sort of
exact wording that comes from the
studies but a conditioned response in
many cases is going to happen with when
your brain is processing a a highly
emotional situation that some of it gets
processed sort of non-consciously some
of it's conscious processing some of
it's non-conscious and it's a way of
protecting you like imagine back
thousands of years ago suddenly there's
a saber-tooth type I don't know if we're
around at the same time as sabertooth
tigers a tiger there's a tiger that
comes out of the Bush and is about to
attack you well in order to protect and
you managed to escape in order to
protect you in future your your body or
your brain is going to pick up on
certain stimuli from the situation that
when you notice those things in future
you're going to react with fear and get
out of the way it's conditioned response
okay it's that's for survival so it
happens from highly emotional situations
but the thing is it's not only from
highly negatively emotional situations
it's also from positive emotional ones
and the trading environment is the
perfect breathing ground for conditioned
responses and so a lot of trading
psychology issues that people have are
actually conditioned responses and
funnily enough a lot of them so let's
put that down lots of
issues are that but many of them
come from when you were
learning
okay because that's when you're risking
too much money forcing trades
overtrading and if you're risking a huge
amount of money like when people have uh
an account where they've got some
leverage and they could be over leverag
that they can risk everything on one
trade and in the space of an hour either
they've lost their entire account or
they've made a huge profit both are
going to be highly emotional experiences
that's going to partly be a conditional
response that shape them for the rest of
their trading career there was a guy
that um got in touch with me a few years
back he was living in Dubai and he said
that he was a very successful Trader he
had a trading system that was working
really well he showed me all the data
and everything but during I think it was
the financial crisis or maybe it was one
of the sort of sovereign debt crisis
after that he made some mistakes that
cost him a huge amount of money so he
went from something like four five
million dollar that he had in capital at
the time to a few hundred, something
like that and you imagine the emotional
experience you're basically when you
make a loss like that you're grieving
and grief can affect you in so many
weird and crazy ways it's is like in
that moment he was probably feeling
suicidal he was worried about his family
I mean this guy's in his
40s so he wanted to have a call with me
and I had this video call like on Skype
his camera comes on and he's got I'm not
kidding you like 20 or 30 screens around
him and he was like this because he used
to have this trading team of like
mathematicians and stuff that were
working on his systems with him and he
couldn't afford to pay them anymore
after he like lost all the money but he
still got all the screens there it was
like looking at like Star Trek or
something or like you know those adverts
for like Tony Robbins where he's facing
all the screens of the people it's like
that right anyway I'm talking to this
guy and he's saying as soon as he opens
the trade now he starts shaking he gets
nervous he's sweating that he has to
close it just to stop the symptoms and
he's like like what's going on I know
when I open a trade it's going to be
profitable because I've got all the data
for my system I know exactly when I
should be entering but I can't keep the
trades open what do I do and it was
because he's got conditioned responses
and this is what happens with beginners
when they use real money they develop
these and then they Wonder lace down the
line why they can't overcome these
simple things like moving their stop-
loss when the price moves towards it
they've learned by then that these
things they're doing are irrational
they're illogical they're only going to
ruin their performance but they can't
help themselves and it's because a
conditioned response a lot of the time
is not coming from your conscious brain
in fact all the time it's not coming
from your conscious brain it's coming
from preconscious thought processes and
preconscious thought process processes
that it's in the the phrase itself
preconscious is happening before your
conscious brain even knows what's going
on but what happens is that your
conscious brain wants to create
narratives and tie things together to
make sense of the world around you so
when you take an action it will you'll
explain why you're doing that action
when actually it wasn't you taking the
action it was your preconscious brain
reacting and you're then explaining why
you were doing it and there was a study
that John coats the neuroscientist
former Trader did with his team where
they were actually assessing Traders on
a Wall Street trading floor and um they
could see the like the volatility in the
markets were in tune with like or like
correlated in some way to um what was
going on in their brain and there were
certain actions they were taking in
relation to that but then they were
explaining it when they were asked about
it um like giving a narrative of what
happened that actually wasn't even
connected with it at all it's really
fascinating we we'll discuss it sometime
but these can become really difficult to
overcome and it's going to take most of
the time like cognitive therapy to
overcome which is much more difficult
and time consuming than just not trading
with real money in the first place also
this makes people more obsessed with the
end goal of making money rather than the
process of learning money rather than
process and I've seen this with lots of
people who go through funding challenges
there was a guy who was working on my
team for a while who um is not with of
us anymore not he's not passed away he's
not on the team anymore I always say
that I always have to correct myself and
he Wast the year because he was just
chasing and chasing funding accounts
like this year before he joined a team
he was chasing funding accounts when he
wasn't ready but because like the the
sort of lure of POS possibly making
money that you don't already have from
your trading uh it's like well why do I
want to go back to the drawing board and
work on my skill it's like you you get
hooked it's an addiction there are some
people in our community who got to the
stage where they thought they were ready
for funding and they said they'll go
through the funding process just as a
learning experience but then it changes
their focus and then they finish that
funding process and rather than it being
the experience The Learning Experience
they thought it was going to be it just
gets them hooked on the cycle of going
for the funding account again so rather
than going back and working on develop
in their skill they just go back to
trying to figure out how to pass the
funding challenge next so if that is
happening early in your trading career
that you're obsessed with the money side
rather than the process it's just going
to lead to the urgency and it's going to
stunt your development so let's move on
to the next point I knew this is going
to be a long video but I think this is
going to be really long uh I'm not sure
if we're going to release it like this
but we'll see if it's dragging on I'm
sorry some of you are going to love it
some of you are going to hate it we'll
see how it goes if it works out then
fine we do more videos like this maybe
um if you want more videos like this let
me know in the comments but don't be a
[__] Karen but luckily I think we can
get through this one quite quickly
because this relates to other things
that we've um we've discussed so first
of all it's important to have a
development plan right you need to be
following a plan and we put a video out
a little while ago about the what we
call our monthly transformation contests
and there's a template there that you
can follow for exactly how to plan uh
what you should be focusing on each
month because you need to have some
something that's the focus you need to
be setting yourself clear goals that's
how you get in a flow State that's how
you avoid getting distracted and going
on these side quests that lead you
nowhere so you need a development plan
and here's the trick right if you work
your way from the end so start with the
end goal and work your way backwards
from there and if you've researched
enough and spoken to enough people that
you can like guarantee that these are
the exact right steps in the right order
and you know that there's no better way
than what you've planned here because if
you just follow these steps if you stay
focused and do these things and hit
these Milestones you will hit your goal
if you can feel that way about your plan
you will stick to your plan because a
lot of the time the the problem people
have is that they put together a plan
that they don't actually fully believe
in as they don't stick to it because in
the moment when they're sat there about
to work on something they feel like
something else is a more pressing issue
more urgent more import to work on uh
because they don't believe in their plan
in the first place so then it makes you
think what's the point of the plan but
it's important with the plan that you
are realistic with it don't set
arbitrary goals or deadlines what do I
mean by that so arbitrary goal is things
like uh I'll
make I'll make uh 100K profit by the end
of the
year by end of year or I'll be
funded this
year these are arbitrary goals goals why
because you don't know if you'll be
ready for these things one like this
well this one is um an arbitrary profit
goal you see you want to set goals that
are fully in your control profit targets
things like that are partly down to the
market and that's not in your control so
what you're going to do end up risking
more to try and hit it if you're not
getting the opportunities it's just it
doesn't make sense but these arbitrary
goals all they're going to do is
accelerate um well make you try to
accelerate your development even when
it's not possible to you're not going to
develop in the way that's like right for
you you're going to try and push ahead
too quickly it's kind of like if you're
going to the gym or something and you've
decided that by the end of the year like
you just started just started at the gym
and you decide that by the end of the
month you're going to bench 100 kilos
right and you've never benched before in
your life then you're going to be
progressing through the weights too
quickly you're going to be ego lifting
you're going to injure yourself you look
like an idiot
um but it just it doesn't make sense and
it's the same thing here it's it's like
if you're setting yourself an arbitrary
goal you're not going in the like you're
not progressing in a way that's right
for you like going to the bench press
example it would be much better to say
that each session I'm going to try to
add an extra rep or up the weight I will
add an extra rep until I hit 12 reps and
then I'm going to up the weight until I
can only do eight reps and then I build
up until I do 12 and so on each session
something like that Progressive overload
same thing same with deadlines right if
I say okay I'm going to be a profitable
Trader by end of
2025 and I just started learning then
who who says like what's that based on
just plucking out a thin air like you
might as well say tomorrow or like 2027
it's no difference instead you'll be
profitable when you're profitable I'm
going to focus on the process these are
the actions I need to take this is the
steps these are the steps that are going
to lead me there whenever I'm going to
work my hardest on each step one at a
time and when I hit the Milestone I'm
ready to progress however long that
takes whatever is needed I will give it
my all that's
all because otherwise it's just going to
lead to higher risk urgency we've talked
about urgency being one of the worst
things uh for someone developing as a
Trader it's just going to mess up your
head you're going to start feeling like
a failure when you're not hitting these
arbitrary goals that you set and for
what reason you just you've plucked them
out of thin air no one's forced you no
one's chasing you you've chosen them and
now you've screwed up your mental health
well
done who am I ranting at everyone I'm
ranting at
everyone okay so number six this is a
really really important one it's so
important that I'm going to do
this circle it I'm going to put a little
stars I want you to pay attention to
this one risk is the volume dial for
trading psychology and that's the
individual trade risk and a personal
risk what that means is the trade risk
when you take a trade and you decide I'm
going to risk 10 15% of my account on
that trade you are amplifying everything
in your mind you are amplifying the loss
aversion that you'll feel you'll have
all of these trading pychology issues or
symptoms that have been dormant that
will suddenly emerge and the reason is
quite
simple your brain handles different
risks and different dangers in a very
similar way so there's a whole list of
them that they found that brain process
in a similar way there's
obviously physical let's put
dangers physical social like are you
going to be embarrassing yourself in
front of the group and out of the group
um and there are others but basically
Financial okay now think about it when
you're in physical danger what do you
feel like Palms are sweating like
there's a whole physiological process
that that happens and then you go
through fight or flight now those of you
who are afraid of public speaking
imagine stepping on stage in front of
thousands of people what's going to
happen your palms are going to be
sweating you might freeze you might go
through fight or flight where you
actually want to get out of
there kick someone's head in if you're
going to fight joking obviously but this
what happens with the financial side as
well there are parts of your brain as I
said before it's like non-conscious it's
the lower parts of your brain the more
primitive parts that are there for
survival and when you think you're in
danger it's going to kick in for that
fight or FL right and your conscious
mind is not going to be processing the
situation or in control of the situation
your survival mechanisms are in control
so the more you increase your risk on
your trade the more financial danger you
potentially have and the less
consciously you're going to be
processing things your loss AV verion is
going to be Amplified and that has so
many different sort of avenues that come
off this that affect your trading in
lots of different ways it basically
means that when you're running in a loss
you'd rather have the uncertainty of
possibly having a bigger loss but
possibly not having a loss at the end of
that so leave the trade running rather
than a certainty of having a loss and
when you move into profit you'd rather
have the certainty of banking that
profit than the uncertainty of having a
bigger profit but also maybe getting
back into a loss in other words you
close your profits too soon and you hold
your losses for too long and the more
money you have at risk the more that's
going to happen because when you're
running into a loss and your draw down
on that open trade is now hitting 5%
you're like sh [__] I don't want to hit
a 5% on my account negative 5% I'll
holds on in case we can come back up
this way uh whereas if that was running
at like a 0.5% you're more willing to
stick to the plan and do what's right
for the trade rather than what's right
for the balance and there are so many
other psychological problems that come
up when you have bigger amounts of risk
like you might lose a lot of money
develop a conditioned response is one
thing but also then put more money in
putting good money after bads because
you want to make that money back maybe
you can't quite afford afford that you
lose that I hear from lots of people
that then get themselves into debt to
try and recover that previous money and
it goes on and on and on and in lots of
cases with some of the really bad retail
Brokers they don't help you because
they'll call you up and be like hey uh
we noticed that you don't have any money
in your account why don't you put some
money in we can help you blah blah blah
and it just the hole gets bigger and
bigger and then people think trading's
gambling it doesn't work and they give
up when really the problem was them
risking too much to begin with so that's
a trade risk and I don't think I need to
go on and on about it you'll find in the
description box videos that relate to
that but the personal risk you know we
said that social dangers as well we will
do what we can to avoid uh losing status
and so if we've set the wrong
expectations with people so if like
there are a few things here so let's say
people's
expectations let's say that we've given
up our job given up job we're relying on
trading for income income um uh We've
set ourselves a
deadline to like got achieve it by this
time or got to do something else like a
lot of people it's surprising how many
times this has come up that someone said
to me oh my parents want me to go to
university or something like that but
they've given me six months to make
trading work or something all these
things or like uh feeling left behind
feeling yeah you get the idea anyway
this creates personal risk these are
increasing the level of Jeopardy with
your Trading so suddenly it's turning up
the risk on that side which means it's
going to affect your trading psychology
you feel more pressure uh every trade is
going to feel like a setback you know uh
this is something that I think we will
we'll probably get to in a little while
as well but if we go back to the the
topic of
scarcity or an
urgency when you have all of these
things it's making each trade feel like
it's scarce and it's urgent because if
you miss an opportunity it's like [__]
now I'm like falling behind I could have
been closer to what I needs to achieve
here or if a trade ends up in a loss
which is expected because probabilities
um you'll feel like it's a setback not
just a setback in terms of money but
also a setback in terms of time so
that's going to lead to you then forcing
trades overtrading and so on so if you
keep your risk in check no more than 2%
of your account at risk
count per trade and there's some
confusion about this sometimes for
people that trade equities we're not
saying 2% of your Capital invested 2% at
risk meaning on any trade the most you
can lose is 2% but that should be the
upper part of your parameter so imagine
that you've got this
scale this your upper and lower
parameters and you can decide what you
want the upper and the lower to be but
the upper should be no more than 2% some
people might say oh I don't feel
comfortable risking that much so maybe
it's 1.5 % and at the lower end well
it's not worth my time to be trading any
less than 0.3% because then I'm earning
less than minimum wage or something like
that then depending on the opportunity
depending on the expectancy or the
probability or whatever you want to base
it on then you you have different
amounts so maybe here it's like okay
this trade's going to be
0.45% oh this one's a really good
opportunity it's going to be 1.7% and so
on it it's dynamic position sizing um
but always keeping a maximum of 2%
because you don't want to have all of
this other [__] kicking in that will
kick in and I know some people will look
at their system they'll look at the
Kelly Criterion and so on and they'll be
like but I could risk more you could but
don't and there's a video Linked In the
description box that explains why the 2%
risk management rule is so
important so let's move on so solve the
root cause most trading psychology
issues are symptoms not the problem
themselves and they all usually come
down to
lack of
skill uh shitty approach method we'll
call
it
or poorly formulated
system we did a whole video about this
explaining how some of the the most
common trading psychology issues are
actually a skill issue you see if you
have um let's say that you've got all of
this sorted you've developed the skill
you are not using a shitty method you're
using a good one and you've got a well
formulated system then what you're going
to end up with
is good
data okay good data it's important that
it's consistent because then you can
rely on it if you're taking a slightly
different approach for each and every
trade your data is going to be
meaningless because you know each trade
is independent but if you if you've got
data from a consistent approach and it
shows you that you have an edge and we
released a video recently about how to
measure your Edge which people disagreed
with me about it because they don't
quite understand it I think but once you
do understand it you'll see that it's a
really great approach and I'm going to
do a follow-up video about that to
explain the things that maybe people
need to understand to see why it's so
good but if you have this most trade and
psychology issues are resolved let's say
for example that we play a coin flip
game this is this is the queen even know
it's now King Charles in there but I
prefer the queen um so you're doing a
coin flip and if it's
heads you're going to make2 and if it's
taals you're going to pay out 1 okay now
let's say that and it's a fair coin
right it's not one of these like
weighted coins that's going to go on one
side of the other it's completely fair
so there's a 50% chance of this and a
50% chance of this so let's say you're
you're flipping this coin and you lose
10 times in a row so you've now had to
give up
£10 are you going to have any issue
flipping the coin the next time no
because you know you've got a a massive
Edge there and you know that over a
short sample size of 10 flips there
could be a lot of variability but over
the long run you're going to be making
money so just flip the coin as many
times you can until the other person
that's paying out all the money realizes
how stupid they are and stops the game
you keep flipping the coin so if you
have good data that shows that you have
an edge you will keep playing the game
you will keep flipping the coin the
problem that people have is that they
don't have good data or they don't have
data at all good or bad they don't
collect it but when you have bad data
it's going to be lack of skill shitty
trading method or poorly formulated
system poorly formulated system is
because that that's what's going to lead
you to
being
inconsistent and lack of skill and
shitty method is going to lead to you
having negative
expectancy if you solve those problems
and you know that you have have an edge
you no longer have most of your trading
issues okay I won't go into much detail
about all this one because we'll link
the video below and I know that I'm
going to let this video get out of hand
otherwise but
um you see the the thing with this this
is just my final Point here
most trading gurus have lack of skill
shitty method poorly formulated system
and there's no way for you to to
actually um test their approach because
it's quite vague it's not nicely defined
where you can say okay these are the
parameters so I can now test it and see
if it does work the way you say it does
like the DW method is nicely defined we
can test it and I've given you the
objective way to test if you have an
edge in one of our last videos which is
what we encourage our members to do to
prove that objectively we have an edge
but most trading gurus will not have
that instead what they do have is a
system that's fairly vagues that they
there's this gray area that they could
say oh no it would have been profitable
if you did this and then they blame
people's psychology no you've got
everything you need for like following
the right approach but you just don't
have the right mindset you're having
like a a loser mindset or whatever like
nonsense nonsense [__] stuff and uh
that's their easy excuse then people
blame themselves rather than blaming the
mentor until they develop enough
experience over time that they see how
illogical all the trading approaches are
whether it's uh you know I'm going to
get myself in trouble just like when I
did the the chart patterns video the
traditional chart patterns when those
were popular and everyone bashed me in
the comments and said I don't know what
I'm talking about then some suddenly
everyone moves on to the next fad
trading approach and then they agree
with me on that one but whether it's the
ICT SMC KFC JCB whatever
approach
just there were illogical things about
them let's leave it at that and it's not
always just about your trading
psychology while you're failing or
succeeding you know those trading
approaches right it's like a circle jerk
in the social media comments and online
it feels like people care more about in
the comments proving that they know
about that technique more than other
people in the comments oh no that's not
an fvg because it's this and this they
care more about that than actually
whether they can test that approach to
see if it's profitable whether it's
working for them they care more about
social status because I think most
people with their trading as long as
they're satisfying that social status
then that's all they need you know
rather than getting it from playing a
computer game they can get it from being
in the comments section on a popular
trading approach but if there are that
many people learning that trading
approach and using it why are not so
many more of them profiting from it it's
just the same as the 95% there's 5% that
are anyway moving on I'm just going to
get myself in trouble here one for this
video being so long and two for making
comments like that always know where or
when your next decision points are
really straightforward whenever you
enter a trade whenever you take an
action even if the action when the
trade's open is to hold and not take any
action that's still a decision that
you've taken when you take that decision
always know when or where or both when
and where your next decisions will be so
let's say that uh I've entered short
here okay and I decide that this is
going to be my next decision Point
decision point
price reaches it and when we get there I
decide I'm going to hold a bit longer
but I now know okay my next decision
point will be if it gets up
here DP no dirty mines please um and
maybe I've got some some analysis that
showed me down here as well so price
gets down here now I decid I'm going to
scale out uh next decision point will be
if it breaks above here next decision
point is going to be down here but
actually there's an economic data
release coming out so now it's
11:30 and maybe by 1:00 I need to make a
decision so by 1:00 the price is here
and I decide to exit the trade now when
you all already know where your next
decision points will be it stops you
being reactive because a lot of people
enter a trade and then the price is mov
and they're like oh should I exit that's
moved quite quickly now let's take the
profit there where it goes against them
like oh that's looking a bit dangerous
let's get out you you take you stop
yourself being reactive and what you're
doing is leaving the decision- making
process for when you're more um rational
when you're when you're thinking clearer
because when you're moving into a profit
or into a loss just like we spoke about
earlier there are certain aspects that
you're reacting like you have physical
reactions automatic behaviors will come
into play emotions and so on if you want
the most Clarity um set your decision
points ahead of time and what the
decision is going to be if it's like
this this if it's like like that that or
if expectancy is positive stay in the
trade if it's above what it was before
scale in if it's gone negative exit the
trade like make things straightforward
but always know where or when your next
decision points are and then it just
solves so many bloody trading psychology
issues most issues it's like people not
knowing what to do next and sort of
dithering and worrying and that's not
how trading should be it should be a lot
more clinical it should be more logical
not so
bloody emotional which is ironic because
we come on to the next point which is
emotions can be an advantage the problem
is you just haven't developed your
awareness of them
yet so everyone always
says you want to be
emotionally
neutral I used to say that as well I
didn't know what I was talking about
clearly well I thought I knew what I was
talking about but the research proves
that I was wrong
and I'm not afraid to say that I was
wrong and I've corrected myself and in
our program we go into a lot of detail
about this it's years I mean I'm talking
years and years ago that I was wrong
with it like for years now we've been
saying about emotions there's a really
long video uh where I've gone into all
of the research and explains how your
brain works and all this sort of stuff
and even more detail in our program but
I'll link it down below link it up here
maybe as well watch it some people like
it cuz we go into the research some
people don't like it because they don't
want to hear about the research you
can't please everyone on YouTube One
idiot comments saying it's most boring
video on
YouTube I'm not here to entertain you
I'm here to talk about trading and teach
you stuff so if you find it boring so be
it I don't care I say that but I do care
I want things to be interesting this one
clearly is not going to be it's just
going to be a long drawn out
conversation but anyway uh the so better
than people saying that you need to be
emotionally neutral is when people say
that they have become emotionally
neutral right this is the clear sign of
when someone is a bullshitter because it
is next to Impossible unless you've got
some form of brain damage to be
emotionally neutral to have no emotions
because we are built to move the
decision making processes that take
place in our brain the sort of the
connections are intertwined with
connections to our body when we think
about something we don't just think
about it in our brain as if our brain is
some computer that's in isolation we
feel it as well that's why in some of
the most emotionally impactful
situations when you have fear love
excitement and so on you don't just
think it you feel it so when things
happen in the markets we feel these
things why because we are built for our
thought processes to lead to action to
lead to movement to lead to us doing
something you can't switch off you can't
sever the connections it just doesn't
happen we aren't this computer we aren't
like the brain in the [__] vas or
whatever V I don't know
container jeez I've been talking too
much brain and AAS that sounds like a
band name an emo band brain and noas I
like that going to trade market so you
can't be emotionally neutral we are
built to move you see the thing
is there are studies about this and my
favorite one is about the C squirt it's
not a study It's actually an analogy but
using the C square and the the analogy
is that if we didn't need to move then
we would wouldn't have a brain like if
we didn't need to to move if we like
stay in one place we wouldn't need the
brain and we would ingest it because a
brain is metabolically expensive takes
up too much energy so the C square has a
brain it moves around until it becomes
the sort of static thing that just stays
in one place I can't remember what they
called now torit or something and it
ingests its brain in order to become
this static thing so it's the same for
us we are built move we're going to feel
the thoughts that we have so you can't
become emotionally neutral then we can
talk about like the sematic marker
hypothesis and how feelings are used as
part of our decision-making process the
reason we're able to make decisions so
rapidly is because we feel the
Alternatives that we're going through to
make a decision there's actually um
stories of uh from neuroscientists who
wrote about this I think it was was it
Joseph Le or was it um deasio I can't
remember from top of my head who had the
patient and he had brain damage that he
wasn't able to feel to make hisc
Decisions by feeling things and they
were seeing if he wanted to make like
when his next appointment should be and
it was taking him so long going through
it because he's thinking about almost
like a big decision tree of all the
different Alternatives but if I go at
this time then this is going to happen
and that interferes with this and going
on and on and on whereas someone could
just be like yeah Thursday 9:00 works
for me because they can feel the
decisions that's an oversimplification
okay but if you watch the video about
emotions I explain it there as well so
we can't become emotionally neutral for
first of all is impossible so what's the
best thing to do is to become aware of
your emotions now there was a study that
was done on investors or maybe it was
Traders basically Market participants
about emotions and decision- making and
what they found was surprisingly the
ones who felt their emotions more
intensely had better returns but there
is a sort of um disclaimer of this which
is that it's if you are aware of your
emotions
so intense
emotions are
good
if you're aware of them so what does
that mean it means being able to notice
and name them so there's I can't
remember the abbreviation that's used
but it's basically this anticipate
notice and name anticipate that you're
going to feel things so rather than
going through your trading session and
be like oh got to the end of I don't
know what I felt anticipate you're going
to feel emotions notice when they emerge
and name what the emotion is the more
specifically you can name and identify
your emotions um the the better you'll
be able to use them for information
we'll come on to the information bit in
a second um so you want to not just be
looking at primary emotions like fear
and so on but also looking at secondary
emotions because the more specific you
can get the better and it comes with
practice not everyone's good at this to
start with but the more you anticipate
notice and name the better you'll get at
it and it's really important you it in
the moment and not afterwards because in
hindsight it changes your view of things
so in the moment you need to be uh
taking note in your trading journal
about these things um so what I would do
is at different points like before
entering a trade during the trade After
exiting the trade and any moments where
you feel emotions emerging you take
notes of it in your Journal you could
also set random alerts for during a day
where the alert goes off and during that
time you just take note in an emotions
tracker uh what you're feeling at at
that time okay then you get better at it
cuz here's the thing emotions carry
information the same way we talked about
conditioned responses we subconsciously
pick up on stimulus from or like
different aspects of a situation we've
been in and store it as information but
we don't have the information
consciously and sometimes we're not even
like we we'll be picking up on such a
subtle thing that consciously we don't
even know like we wouldn't even be aware
of this thing at all like we didn't pick
up in the first place we're not picking
up on now but it might be important
information you know when you walk down
a street and just something makes you
feel uneasy like something bad's about
to happen and then it does and you're
like I knew that was going to happen
that's that same kind of thing so I
won't go through the examples because
they're in that long video and I know
this video is going to drag on and on if
I go through every example and reiterate
what I've said in other videos but watch
that video watch it in detail take notes
and process it and think about what that
means for your trading and what you'll
realize is that you've been lied to
about emotions being a disadvantage they
can be an advantage as long as you're
aware of them because they're giving you
information that you wouldn't have
otherwise and what is it about trading
that's going to help you to succeed is
having better information and processing
it
better so let's move on to the next
point which is to develop your
probabilistic thinking and to rely on
probabilities more all right I's take a
break from the screen for a second just
in case it uh sounds different or looks
different or anything now you'll know
why now before we come to this point I
want to point out that I talk about
probabilities a lot on this channel and
it's something I'm going to go on and on
about this year because it's the one
thing I've noticed that in the trading
industry everyone says like trading is a
game of probabilities but people don't
use probabilities as part of their
trades they just use it as like
understanding their success rate or some
other nonsense and so I keep putting out
videos explaining situations where
probability so important or ways to use
probabilities to improve your trading
ways to measure your accuracy of
probabilities
and it's because it's so important and
so I just want to point out for this one
there's a link down in the description
box to a free training and please just
go and sign up for it and keep an open
mind and watch the whole training and
it's like an hour long and I'm going to
explain different elements of this to
you so that you can sort of understand
the point of view and then in the weeks
after that I'm going to send you more
free training of different things that
are going to help your trading and help
you to think more
probabilistically that's the right word
to use also in the description box while
I'm at it there are other free resources
there uh one of them which is extremely
relevant to this topic is how to track
your trading and to keep a trading
journal even if you are keeping a
trading journal go and download that
it's a free pdf it's quite detailed just
in case there's something that you're
missing there that could be helpful for
you or if you haven't started keeping
one yet you need to keep one all of this
stuff we're going through keeping a
journal is going to help you track
what's going on in your mind and how to
improve your trading session how to
improve your trading performance um in
so many different ways so go and
download that PDF and then so I'm also
trying to log into my iPad at the same
time because I've got my notes here but
there's also one about uh transforming
your trading PDF which relates to the
video that I mentioned earlier that's
about how to structure things like each
month what to focus on to improve your
trading so again a detailed PDF for you
we give so much away for free you don't
even have to like I would recommend
joining our Trader development program
honestly it's the most detailed the most
comprehensive training out there we go
in so much research in the different
areas related to trading psychology our
trading approach is logical you can
objectively measure how it's working or
whether it's working uh we have a great
community and if you want to join that
then I'd recommend going through our
free stuff first our free stuff is much
better than everyone's paid stuff
because they haven't got the experience
or they haven't really care in the way
that we do um and if you decid no I
don't really care about your trading
approach I just want to learn the
psychology side then send us an email
and we can sort out you get an access to
the Psychology and Neuroscience sections
of the program instead although as
you'll find out later or in fact as
we've already been through um most
trading psychology issues are resolved
from the trading approach itself and the
skill side so I think it's much better
if you actually go through the full
program but anyway I thought I'd mention
that now because otherwise it will get
lost somewhere in the video and I want
to make a point of it because I feel
like a lot of people don't realize how
much value we can give you just from
signing up and that we actually care
about helping your trading and it's not
just something we say it's something we
actually show and we do unlike what you
see elsewhere so developing your
probabilistic thinking and relying on
probabilities more now these are two
separate things they might sound like
they're the same but it's actually in
terms of trading psychology two separate
things so probabilistic
thinking when you start quantifying the
probabilities of a situation it changes
the way that your your brain processes
the situation so there
was a guy about a century ago or so who
um and again I'm doing this off the top
of my head so I can't think of the top
of my head who it was now what his name
was it will come to me who made the
distinction between a risk and an
uncertainty so a risk is something with
quantifiable probabilities and an
uncertainty is something that has no
quantifiable probabilities so for
example to to give you the difference
between the two um imagine that I have
two glass jars not a vs with a brain in
it this time two glass jars and we've
got red and blue balls in them each of
them one of them I tell you there's 60
red balls and 40 blue balls and the
other one I tell you I don't know like
I'm not going to tell you how many of
each are in there but both have 100
Balls but one you know it's 6040 the
other one you don't know and I say you
can choose one and if you pick out the
blue ball you're going to get a 10er
okay £10 then most people are going
choose the one with the quantifiable
amount well like the one that's the risk
not the uncertainty so this one's a risk
this one's an uncertainty the one that's
quantifiable is risk the other one's
uncertainty now Studies have been done
on these uh to show what people prefer
what people feel more comfortable with
but also what goes on in your brain and
your brain actually processes a risk and
an uncertainty differently so just from
quantifying the probabilities of a
situation with a trade and you turn it
from an uncertain into a risk your brain
I'm going to draw a brain like this
look this is a brain your brain
processes it this the frontal cortex
there we go brain your brain process it
differently with an uncertainty then
it's relying a lot more on things like
your amydala it's going to be more
emotionally driven because think about
it uh if you hear a noise and you like
if like if thousands of years ago you
hear a noise that sounds like it could
could be a present you don't know like a
loud noise so you're not sure what it is
then what sort of response are you going
to want more of like a fear-based one
automatic response get the [__] out of
there whereas if it's like a loud noise
but you can hear that it's actually it's
a tiger having a fight with something
else and it's not related to you and
they they're attacking each other a
hippo and a
tiger I'm probably coming out some
absolute nonsense these things probably
can't even happen then it's a risk and
you can actually decide based on the
probability you can make a logical
decision okay so they sound like they're
by The Watering Hole um they aren't near
me they're more engaged with each other
I'm probably okay being where I am now
but I should start moving my way away
from there when the noise stops that I
know that they're not attacking each
other anymore suddenly your decision-
making could be more logical it's not so
like [__] get the [__] out of here it's
like thinking it through um so it's
about quantifying the probabilities that
it changes the way your brain works so
it's not not just about probabilistic
thinking for your trades but just life
in general everything's about
probabilities you don't realize it but
when you're making decisions in your
everyday life you're making assessments
of probabilities estimates of
probabilities we use something in our
day-to-day life called basian
cognition and it's surprisingly accurate
and it's something we'll talk about in a
separate video when we talk about why um
why the approach that I was explaining
before about measuring your
is so useful and how people are
estimating probabilities without
realizing they are I'm going to prove it
in that video and we'll talk about it
more then so developing your
probabilistic thinking but also then
relying on probabilities more this is
going to improve your trading psychology
in many ways so first of all this is
going to stop you reacting with like
fear and and all that kind of stuff and
being sort of it's going to stop you
from being preconscious or non-conscious
and be more consciously thinking about
things okay and it's also that you can
measure your success much better and be
more dependable but that relates to this
relying on your probabilities more the
the biggest thing here is it's going to
stop you hesitating with your trades
most Traders when they open a trade
they're trying to make the they're
trying to decide whether they think that
trade is going to end up in a profit or
not so they will accept logically
rationally that trading is a game of
probabilities there's always a chance of
losing and a chance of profiting but
then when they come to open a trade
they're saying do I think this will be a
profit and what that means is that
they're trying
to go from having uh
uncertain an uncertain situation they're
somehow trying to transform that into
being a certain situation but they can't
if it's an uncertainty they can't
transform it the markets to an extent
are
uncertain so they're trying to answer a
question that's impossible for them to
answer now when we're trying to figure
something out like that our brain goes
through a strategy known as
explore
exploit so explore means looking for
more information until eventually we've
got enough information that we can
exploit but the problem is if
something's uncertain your explore phase
is looking for a certainty that doesn't
exist you know when people are looking
for all these different signs that that
add up to a trade entry where they're
adding more indicators and looking for
all this Confluence I see it all the
time on YouTube as well from people that
are like uh showing off that they're
really successful there's there's one
guy who um I can't I can't name names
yet at some point I'll do that but I
don't want the drama um he just talks
about oh these are all the the different
strategies that I use and he's just
layering them on top of each other he's
like one of the most popular ones on
YouTube but it's nonsense all it is the
case of uh over thee toop exploring
because you're trying to uh somehow by
increasing the amount of information
you're trying to gain more certainty but
all you're doing is increasing your
confidence level not Cy level and
they're two different
things so people get in this endless
cycle it's like people Doom scrolling on
the news when like Co was around that
they're trying to look for some
certainty in a situation that was
uncertain the way that we move to the
exploit phase is to have some sort of
trigger when is it enough when have we
explored enough when do we start to
exploit and the way to do this is to
rely on
probabilities if you say that you're
going to enter a trade when it's
positive expectancy
positive expectancy being uh positive
outcome multiplied by probability of
that minus negative outcome multiplied
by the probability of that so if that's
positive okay I'm going to enter the
trade well now when are you going to
when is it the time to trigger that at
the point where I have enough
information I can estimate the
probabilities How will I know when it's
time to estimate the probabilities my
system dictates that my system is going
to tell me the steps I need to follow
what factors I need to to consider for
estimating the probabilities when I've
ticked those boxes I know I can now
estimate the probabilities and then I
can exploit if it's positive expectancy
and then you say yeah but how do you
know like at this stage if your
probability is going to be accurate you
collect them up all like collect all of
them up over time and then use what we
talked about in that video of the epbr
calibration and that's going to help you
see over time if if you're accurate
you're not looking at whether each
individual one is accurate it's
impossible to know so rely on the
probabilities more likewise with like
your your trading performance like
having a losing streak uh having a great
month bad month well it's all based on
probabilities if you know the data from
your system overall you can understand
the probability of having a losing
streak of 10 losses in a row it'll be a
much higher percentage than you think
people often use the wrong calculation
for it if you use losing Street
calculator you can figure out better
just briefly
the the way people get that calculation
wrong is that they look at they they do
like the simple calculation that's
effectively telling them what's the
chance of like 10 losses in a
row in the next 10 trades okay and
that's not the right calculation because
of course that's going to be a really
low percentage they're always like oh
there's only like a 0.56% chance of that
so I'm fine with this approach instead
what you need to look at is what's the
chance of 10 losses in a row at any time
in a th trades and that's a very
different calculation and the percentage
is going to be much much higher like if
you have a uh let's say that your your
success rate or your probability is
50%
then that was 5 nor3 50% then this is
going to be very low but this one's
going to be extremely
high okay
so relying on probabilities stops you
panicking when you have a losing streak
we and stops you then changing things
with your system or doing things that
are counterproductive and are only going
to sabotage you and developing your
probabilistic thinking is going to help
you make more logical decisions and to
um not feel so emotional and so worried
and anxious all the time with your
trades but to actually make the right
decision for your
system so let's move on to number 11
experience solves many issues so a lot
of the things that you're going through
if you're learning you won't have that
anymore if you're still trading 10 years
down the line so I started learning as I
said back in around 2002 when I first
came across the game City Trader and got
obsessed with the markets and it's a
rubbish game and I always mention it but
uh it's what got me hooked and over this
many years now I have opened thousands
and thousands of Trades okay and so
there's lots of experience that comes
from that some experience that like of
panicky situations I've been through
that now I know how still of them uh
good situation how to manage
um well manage many different things but
basically like the way that you get more
like mentally tough it's the same as as
most other things that it's a cycle that
involves
um
stress
recovery now too much stress is bad but
a good amount of stress like something
that's not going to put you in a bloody
mental hospital uh is good and then you
recover from it and then you can deal
with more stress and it's basically like
a progressive overload kind of thing so
over time experience is going to help
you achieve that experience is also
going to give you implicit
knowledge so this is like a implicit
sort of statistical understanding of
situations rather than explicit rules
and stuff like being able to spot things
in situations that other people aren't
able to spot and many other things
there's a whole list of like what the
difference is between experts and
beginners um who is
it that wrote it was a Gary Klein maybe
that put together that list I'm not sure
um but anyway there's a whole list of
things that that's developed through
time that's developed through experience
but there's also something else that
comes from experience like all of these
things will solve most trading
psychology issues because there's
nothing really that throws you off by
that point you've experienced it before
and realized like the reality of
situations but there's something else
and it's quantity of Trades
of
Trades when you've opened thousands and
thousands of Trades as I have over the
years you stop feeling the
scarcity and urgency have you noticed
that my handwriting is getting worse and
worse we going through this cuz I'm
writing quicker you stop feeling this
why because when you miss an opportunity
you don't feel like oh [__] I missed
that one like as if it's like the the
scarcity thing is like when you miss a
trade it's almost like one of a limited
amount is gone like imagine there was
only ever going to be five trades and
you miss one oh [__] there's only four
more left that's the scarcity mindset
when you've opened thousands of Trades
you know the next one's just around the
corner likewise the urgency that you
don't feel in a trading session if
nothing was appropriate for entering a
trade and so you don't open a trade you
don't feel like towards the end of the
session oh [__] I better open something
I'm a Trader I'm meant to be trading
because you know they'll come I've had
thousands of Trades they'll come it's
fine or when you lose trades because
losing is part of it like if I enter a
trade that's uh like a 3 to one well it
should be that way around 3 to one
risking one to make three that means
even the base rate probability is going
to be 25% and 75% even if I've got an
edge an edge doesn't completely reverse
that it's still going to be I've got
more chance of losing the trade than
profiting from it but over time it's
going to succeed like it's going to lead
to a positive Traders equation so I'm
opening that trade knowing there's a
good chance that I'm going to lose so
when I do lose a trade like that I'm not
now thinking oh this is a big setback um
I all that time that I wasted waiting
for that trade I've now got to claw back
like that bit of draw down or like I was
up 10% this month for now I'm only up 8%
how can I get that back so I can
withdraw some like some money from the
account and whatever you don't feel that
anymore because you know that each trade
is just like an individual snowflake an
individual snowflake I'm not talking
about snowflakes that are going to
complain in the comments about this
being a 10 million hour video each
individual snowflake on its own is
insignificant but an accumulation of
many of them can be an avalanche or can
be a snowman something important like
that and that's the same with trading
you start to have the perspective see
experience leads to
perspective perspective there we go but
the thing is that's like saying that to
you now let's say you just started
trading a couple of months ago so what
okay great so some of my trading
psychology issues are going to be fixed
10 years from now 20 years from now
brilliant that's really helpful right
now now there are some aspects of the
experience that you cannot get any other
way than the passing of time but there
are some that you can get quicker some
aspects of experience and one of them is
this quantity of Trades get yourself
into a trading simulator yes it's not
real money a lot of people complain
about that but trust me it's the most
important thing to use a trading
simulator the right way and again
there's going to be a video I linked up
here or in the description for our
Ultimate Guide to a trading simulator
it's a long video explaining how to use
it and the different ways that it can
help your trading and down there as well
you'll find a code for getting a
discount from my recommended trading
simulator if you want to get yourself
one go in a trading simulator dedicate
time to just going through and getting
trade after trade after trade to give
yourself that perspective you are also
going to G
implicit knowledge but you're going to
get that perspective from having the
quantity of Trades when you've open
thousands of Trades and be realistic
with the amount of time as well like
let's say pick euro dollar and go over
the course of one year and open all the
trades in that year you're going to gain
perspective and be like okay if I miss a
trade it's not the end of the world
because I'm not going to get one trade
per year like there are many trades here
just stay focused if I keep missing
trades okay fix that issue but don't
panic don't Revenge trade or you know
get fomo because you missed the last
trade and now you you want to miss the
next one so you're jumping in too early
or whatever like it gives you
perspective that you just trade your
your system because you know then after
a thousand trades I've traded my system
I've traded how I meant to be trading
and my data is amazing my returns are
amazing why would I do anything that
deviates from that just be like a robot
and just trade exactly how you meant to
be trading and I'm saying trade like a
robot as in be repetitive not as in
don't have any emotions because as we
know emotions are an advantage so gain
that experience um
it's also like this stops other sort of
cognitive biases and things like that
there's one in particular that I see a
lot of time with Traders um it's called
The Break Even effect it was discovered
by Richard tlor and uh another person
that wrote the paper with him the break
even effect is basically when you're in
a draw down you're more willing to take
big risks if it gives you the
opportunity to get back to break even
and this is especially what people do on
funding accounts but what happens is
that it's a matter of time before that
goes wrong and the hole gets bigger but
again when you have a higher quantity of
Trades that you've taken when you are
thinking in terms of probabilities and
relying on probabilities like the last
point it's going to stop you falling
into those traps because you know that
what's expected from your system and the
best way to get out of the situation is
not to take big risks not to gamble not
to YOLO the account but to stick with
the plan okay so the next one is
gradually adjust to new levels of
capital so I mentioned towards the start
of the video that my most difficult time
from a mental point of view was actually
after I went full-time with my trading
this is after i' made half a million
pounds in profit I was managing capital
for other people we were setting up an
investment fund I was a professional
Trader but I found it very difficult to
adjust to new amounts of capital now
I've seen this with so many Traders over
the years it's I can count on one hand
the number of traders who have told me
that they don't experience this but you
see when you first start trading with
real money and this like when people say
that you should learn with real money
and I've said earlier that I don't think
it's right I think that comes later in
in the development process but the whole
reason is that when you have real money
on the line it changes your decision-
making process uh you get the fight or
flight response a lot more and Things
become like survival a bit more and you
kind of overcome that at the start of
your career like when you you first get
used to like trading with real money you
won't experience that so much anymore
but then there'll be certain like
Milestones that you hit where it comes
back certain amounts of money where
you're risking the same percentage of
your account the process the the same
but for whatever reason the actual
monetary amount there changes your
mindset and you it takes a while to
overcome it so for some people it might
be when the amount they profit or lose
on each trade is the same amount that
they were earning from a month in their
their job or uh the same amount as a car
or a house or whatever it might be like
it's an amount of money that that
affects you emotionally in some way so
when you hit those sort of Milestones it
can feel a bit like a plateau and it's
like you start making the wrong
decisions you start panicking and you
can very quickly spiral into a negative
situation so instead the best thing you
can do is to gradually get yourself to
those amounts of money if you realize
that things are changing for you when
you're hitting a certain amount of money
it doesn't matter if it's the same
percentage at risk as what you were
risking before you should lower it so if
you remember earlier on I was talking
about these these parameters that you
might have let's say that your upper
limit was always 1.5% and your lower
limit was 0.5% right and let's say that
this amount it was fine when this was
£1,000 and as soon as this starts to
become £5,000 let's say then you're
going into psychological
meltdown so in that case what you need
to do is reduce the parameters so that
this this halfway point is maybe like
4,000 or 3,000 whatever amount is
comfortable for you and then slowly
increase it over time and the way that
you can do this is similar to graded
exposure which is a therapy technique
and essentially what you're going to do
there's a few steps to this process but
I'm going to give you like the high
level view of it there are two things
you need you need a relaxation technique
and you need a way of tracking how
you're responding to the the situation
so you're going to start off let's say
your tracking technique is like a heart
rate
monitor and relaxation techniques it
could be meditation breathing focusing
on your breathing brething that kind of
thing so you're going to start off with
an amount of money where your heart rate
doesn't change when you're making a
decision so you're opening a trade your
heart rate doesn't change let's say that
amount for you is like when there's only
£1,000 of risk
okay then you're going to gradually
increase it and let's say you increase
it to 1,200 your heart rate goes up a
bit but you stay at that level until
your heart rate goes back to normal and
you gradually increase it a bit more and
a bit more it's kind of like grade
exposure there are a few therapy types
that are sort of in that whole category
that dis relates to those and each time
you get to a point where your heart rate
is going uploads you take a step back
and you just you're basically just doing
little bits little bits uh to get
yourself comfortable and you only
increase your Capital at the point where
your heart rate is in the region where
you're going to be making logical
decisions or it's not that your heart
rate is leading to those decisions it's
just a symptom of being in a heightened
emotional state so that's one thing is
to gradually increase your amount of
money and this is especially true for
funded
accounts a lot of people going for
funded accounts because the most money
they have in the world is the amount
they pay for the fee for the funded
account which means that when they
suddenly have like 20000 Grand available
to them it's like something they're not
used to and they don't realize that
their emotions go spiraling and they
lose the account quicker than it took
them to get the account in the first
place so with funded accounts this is
really important you could just
gradually sort of introduce bits of bit
more Capital as you go along um but the
other thing that relates to all this
also relates to Def fund of account
which is the contrast
effect when you have big increases or
decreases in capital it creates this
contrast effect that can really mess
with your decision- making and the the
most important one for this is if you
get used to with a fund account let's
say you have a fund account that's
200k and each time you open a trade
you're risking 1% of it so you're
risking
2K and you feel comfortable with that
then something happens the the funding
company goes under you lose the account
whatever and you're back to your own
Capital that you've saved up over time
and it's
10K like the contrast effect it can lead
to you taking big risks on this maybe
it's not 2K maybe it's like a bit less
than that or whatever but you end up
taking positions that you shouldn't be
taking and vice versa it can it can be
the opposite where you're taking really
small positions on the bigger account
and so on but basically you just want to
gradually adjust to the different levels
of capital and between each phase of the
fund account so when you if it's like a
two-stage thing where you got to do the
challenge then the whatever the thing is
after the validation I don't know what
they call it these days um I can't
remember but after the first stage take
a break then when you're completely back
to normal go for the second stage and
especially if you do get funded before
you go and trade on the main account
take a big break that you reset because
in most cases the way that you're
trading to get the account in the first
place is not going to be the same as how
you want to trade to make things
sustainable over the long term or at
least it shouldn't be because the best
way to pass the funding accounts is
actually to use an approach that isn't
sustainable over the long term that's
not something we'll discuss in this
video
but just make sure you gradually adjust
because when I had my meltdown it was
because I was then trading bigger
amounts of money the more responsibility
I felt for that meant that I wasn't
sleeping as much it meant that I had
more stress all the time like chronic
stress 24/7 I was feeling stressed when
I opened a trade uh just from seeing the
amount that had a risk it was like
eating me up inside and I ended up
getting very ill and I spoke about it in
the video which I'll link up here and in
the description box which I actually
referred to earlier as well okay the
camera just cut off and I don't know
where it did so hopefully I've covered
everything that's here but if I haven't
then um you can ask me about what's
written here and I'll explain it but the
next one is to do your inner work
outside of your trading career now this
one it becomes really obvious when
you've worked with so many different
Traders you see the benefit of my
position is that I have gained a lot of
experience from trading for myself so
over 20 years I've been obsessed with
the markets so that's more than what
you'll find for most Traders online in
the first place then I've worked with a
lot of really experienced really
intelligent people both Traders and
other sort of functions from financial
services and risk and things like that
that I've been able to learn from them
or get advice from them then I've also
helped hundreds if not thousands of
Traders around the world at different
stages in their their career which means
that there are certain patterns that I
can pick up on that you wouldn't gain if
you only had one perspective if I was
saying everything just from my
perspective well you might be completely
different to me but there are certain
principles or certain patterns that
emerge that happen for everyone that are
like really common and the only way
you'd know that is by interacting with
so many different Traders and one of
those things is about things affecting
your psychology that are not related to
your trading and most people in that
situation not realizing that that's the
case so you can have traders who are
extremely talented maybe making positive
returns or have the skill set that they
should be able to and they are holding
themselves back in in some way and it's
because of things that are unrelated to
their trading and it's things related to
let's get I've got a bit of a lag going
on here not surprised the lag's
happening in my brain at this point as
well uh it'll be things to do with past
experiences uh
upbringing culture yeah there's a lag so
my writing is going to get even worse um
the people around them so let's say
influence and all of this is going to to
affect their
self-esteem their Identity or
self-image what they feel comfortable
with and that relates to success and
failure as well expectations so on so on
like having an example of someone
succeeding and so on and this comes out
in the market in so many different ways
there's a lot of transference that
happens where people put their past
experiences on the markets I think
Denise sha talks about this a lot where
it's like um the Market's like a parent
or something or there's a a guy on my
team mccy who um is wanting to to do
research into um attachment Theory and
how that relates to trading and
parenting Styles so reparenting and
things like that so we'll maybe discuss
some of that in the future video Once
he's gone into the research with that
but basically there's there's so much
baggage that we have that affects us
that can make you feel like you're never
going to make it that no matter how
successful you are you can always
convince yourself that you're a failure
when you open a trade you can always
have the assumption that it's going to
lose and be pessimistic about it and it
changes the way you make decisions with
that trade um it will change the way
that you do your trade management it
will change the way that you actually
find opportunities in the first place
because if you are pessimistic you'll
find reasons to explain why you
shouldn't take a trade even in
situations where you should so it's like
pessimism
[Music]
and it's kind of heartbreaking to watch
because you see people who are really
talented like really intelligent and
there are people who don't have the
skill that they have uh who are sort of
surpassing them and you can see that
actually the thing that's affecting them
is not from their trading it's from
other things in their life and so you
need to do the inner work outside your
trading and unfortunately this takes
time and effort and it means
journaling not just for your trades and
your Trading session but also just
general life if you think that's going
to help you and a big one is like
therapy I know there's a lot of people
that say therapy is like a waste of
money waste of time because this this
whole sort of red pill [__] that changed
the way people feel about it but I've
been doing therapy now for coming on to
what is it like two and a half years I
think it is every Friday it's been very
helpful for me it's not sitting there
talking about how you're feeling it's
just processing processing information
and understanding yourself more and
realizing okay this has led to this
that's led to this that's that's why I
process things in this way now but I can
see now it's because of this or it's
irrational and I can reframe it or you
know there's all kinds of things or it's
about just making better decisions
because you got someone else that's
sounding board that understands you um
but you need to do that inner work you
need to understand what's really going
on in your brain why are you the way
that you are and how is that being
reflected in your trading how is that
being reflected in the way that you are
in the markets it's so funny you get
like in many different aspects of
trading it's like you have sort of
spectrum and there'll be people over
here and over here and people in the
middle and you think why are they there
or there they looks like I've drawn a
frog now weird weird frog there um there
go give him some ears as well now he's
like a weird
bear
but jeez you start thinking why why why
is this person here and this person is
here well it's not because of the
training they've gone through because
they're both learning at Doo so it's
about past experiences it's about
personality it's about risk profile and
uh all kinds of things so there are some
things that you need to work on outside
your trading and it's worth it it's
really worth it it's as men it can feel
like soft to go and do it or like you
you don't want to be vulnerable and
think about things from your past you
want to be stoic and think ever forward
and so on but it's if it's going to help
your your performance in some way then
why the [__] not just go for it that's
what I thought and that's what I did and
it's benefited me in so many ways I'm
such a better Trader now than I was even
like 13 years ago when I went full-time
for the first time and and was making
amazing money then I'm like light years
ahead of where I was then and it's
because of things like that and from
being more logical and doing the
research and yeah things that I'm
talking to you about so the next thing
which relates to that also relates to
condition responses and so many other
things and we go through this very
quickly is that you need to track
irrational behavior and thoughts track
the automatic responses that you have to
things that you think are unhelpful um
you know not where you've gone through a
thought process and you've said okay I
think the trade's doing this therefore
I'm going to take so I think the price
doing this therefore I'm going to take
this action with my trade but more like
what were the things that you did
without thinking about it that in
hindsight you think that was a bit
irrational I shouldn't have done that
you need to take notes of them and the
best way to do that I've found this is I
think it's like the closest thing to
collecting data on your emotions and
thought processes is to use what we call
the ab CD e sequence c d e sequence and
you could do this in your trading
journal so a
is the activating
event okay so what was it in the markets
that triggered this particular thought
process maybe it was the price
approaching your stop-loss for example
so or maybe it was like the suddenly
volatility kicked in and the price was
moving really fast so B what were the
beliefs or thoughts so belief
thoughts that were triggered as a result
of that activating event so when price
is moving really fast what did you start
thinking oh I can maybe make some profit
here whatever it might be or when the
the price hit your stop loss and you
really down you felt like this is
meaning you're a failure you're
attaching yourself Worth to your trades
see as
consequences what happened
next the because the price is moving
really fast and I believe this is a
chance to make profit I jumped into a
trade when I shouldn't have
okay then we have or maybe it's that the
the price at my stop l i felt like a
failure and as a result then I stopped
trading for two weeks or I uh went out
for beers and went on a negative spiral
went on a
bender the next one is
disputation so you need to argue against
this you need to give the the opposite
like imagine that someone else is saying
that negative thing to you or the
inappropriate belief or thought you need
to give the other side of it you know a
lot of the time like when we when we go
through the inner talk stuff which um
you'll find it linked below and at the
end of this video a lot of that inner
talk that we like the negative inner
talk that we give ourselves if it was
someone else saying that to us we
wouldn't stand for it we wouldn't listen
to them we we'd argue back and defend
ourselves and so it's that that kind of
thing and then is efforts for
change for change so what can you do in
future to avoid this based on this
disputation okay and if you collect
these up in a spreadsheet each time you
just like note these things down you can
start to find uh where there are
recurring triggers like activating
events where there are recurring beliefs
that are associated with different
activated events where there's recurring
consequences because we often deal with
situations in a similar way and actually
when things get very emotional we can
revert back to our previous times of
dealing with things which is why you
often find grown adults that are like
babies when they don't get their own way
like the carens in the comments that are
complaining that I'm going on for ages
enjoy but you you're basically
collecting data and what this means is
that you can figure out where there are
maybe um conditioned responses that need
to be worked on that you can use
cognitive therapy to get through that to
to overcome it um and we'll talk about
that in the the final step where there
are maybe flaws that could be fixed
through your system things Like rules
that you can put in place to mitigate
things now my rule is that I don't like
to set a rule to mitigate something if I
haven't tried to identify the root cause
and solve that first as I said earlier
lots of trading psychology problems most
of them are just symptoms and not the
root cause and if you find the root
cause you can solve that and the
tradeing psychology issue just
disappears so you don't necessarily want
to have rules that's how you become like
restricted by all these different things
you need to do you don't want to always
add things sometimes about removing
things or changing things so collecting
all of this is the best way it's the
closest thing we get to data on this
sort of stuff the other thing you can do
is track your heart rate during trading
sessions but um I didn't put that in
this video I didn't want to discuss it
too much apart from when we're talking
about graded exposure because I want
these to be the 15 principles that I
think by sticking to it you're
definitely going to get yourself on the
right track rather than just like the
nice to have things that are for anyone
that's a bit extra which I am extra so I
would do the heart rate monitor if I was
you um but we can discuss that another
time so then we get on to the final one
which is overcome automatic behaviors by
identifying outliers so this is taken
from cognitive
therapy when we find these things that
we keep doing that we don't want to be
doing let's say that you keep moving
your stop loss and it leads to you
getting this big hole in your like huge
draw down that you didn't want to have
obviously no one wants a draw down but
you let something spiral out of control
your immediate thing is like think about
what rules can I put in place what can I
do that's going to stop me doing that
you're looking online for the quick
fixes and then you come across all the
trading psychology videos that are
rubbish that give you solutions that
don't even work that just passed on from
one generation to another of traders
that date back a century ago and have no
relation to science just going ranting
again but you're looking for a way to
stop that irrational automatic Behavior
but in many cases when you look at
cognitive therapy you don't want to look
at how you stop that behavior instead
you want to replace it with something
else so what you need to do and this is
is also why you need to start using a
trading journal so you can track it but
also was right Journal also the
ABCD that we just went through that's
going to help you track these as well
because you're going to see okay there's
a theme here these things so what you
want to do is not look for the
situations where you went through the
automatic Behavior but look for the
Times where you had the same trigger the
same stimulus that usually triggers so
the same activating event but then you
didn't go through with that pattern of
behavior you didn't take the action
that's usually a disaster so price was
approaching your stoploss and you left
your stop loss and let it get hit so you
find those occasions the exceptions the
outliers so you're going
to find the
exceptions and you're going
to describe them in detail
you're going to relive
them in
detail and by doing so you're going to
identify alternative positive actions
there positive actions actions there we
go you can't tell what it says it looks
like it says fruit but identify
alternative positive actions so now when
you're in that situation it's almost
like
um you you're getting the stimulus but
by going over and over the positive
behavior pattern instead you're finding
something that's been proven in the past
that this can happen and you're you're
just shifting your behavior response to
something that's more productive so what
was it that you did that time that you
left your stop- loss there what were you
thinking what were you doing did you
step away from the screen did you sit on
your hands what were you doing now you
know in future okay from now on I'm
going to do XY Z and that's going to
avoid me taking that behavior so you
haven't stopped like you haven't fought
against that behavior in a way of like
okay I'm going to be consciously aware
each time I'm doing this thing I'm just
going to not do it you found a different
Behavior response that you're going to
try and make the Habit in that situation
that will avoid that thing
happening and just related to that is
that if you've gone through the other 14
points and from your ABCDE Journal
you've figured out that there are things
that are like deeply embedded perhaps
conditioned responses that you caused
when you were learning to trade and
risking too much money and making all
those mistakes then there are cognitive
behavioral
techniques let's say
cognitive
therapy such as grad of the exposure
that we talked about earlier is a good
one and there are others as well and we
talk about these in in the D traded
development program as well as many
other things so look I know this has
been a very very long video I didn't
want to script it because a lot of the
time I feel like when I script things
then although I'm going through the
research and it's more succinct it feels
a bit distant between my experiences and
you know what I'm telling you it comes
across like I'm just teaching a lesson
rather than telling you this is from
over 20 years experience you should
listen to this so I know that some of
you would have hated that this has gone
on so long most people probably dropped
off after about the first 10 minutes or
something or less so if you got to the
end thank you um I want to encourage you
to go in the description box find those
links for the free uh downloads the free
resources the free training honestly we
put so much effort and thought into this
it's not just something we throw
together to think how do we get people
to sign up it's we we think through the
whole process that someone goes through
so sign up make use of all of that you
don't have to join the program although
I definitely recommend it and if you are
convinced that you don't want to learn
our approach but you just want the
trading psychology stuff send us an
email contact doomoo initiative.com let
us know and we can try and get you
hooked up with that um it was a package
that we used to offer a while ago and we
we don't offer it anymore but for the
sake of this video we can offer it again
uh if you liked the video leave a
comment below let me know which points
were particularly helpful for you please
take them all on board please try with
them because honestly it will get you
really close to being free of most the
issues that you're experiencing with the
psychological side hit the Thumbs Up
Button if you liked this and if you want
more videos like this um and on screen
you're going to see two videos that
we'll link here one is the one about
emotions that refer to a lot it's really
detailed it goes through the research I
really recommend just committing and
watching that and the other one is the
selft talk tool kit because even though
we haven't talked about negative selft
talk that much I think a lot of the
things that are in there like creating
rituals and how you uh like the mental
chat how you approach that journaling
and all this kind of stuff will be
really helpful for your trading
psychology in general so check those out
and thanks for watching I'll see you
soon